[GinTama]
[Benizakura Arc]
[Final Episode]
[Yeah]
["On A Moonless Night, Insects Are Drawn To The Light"]
♪♪～
After living a long time in darkness, I perceived a light too faint for the eyes to see.
《似蔵:長いこと
闇の中にあると➡
目玉には映らん わずかな光さえ
拾えるようになる｡
I don't recall when I learned that the light radiated from human beings.
ｿｲﾂが
人間の放つものだと知ったのは➡
いつだったか…｡
It shines brightest, like a brilliant flower of light, just before they die.
線香花火のように
人間も また 消えいくとき➡
ひときわ大きく
美しい花を咲かす｡
だが 稀に ｺｲﾂを生きながらに
背に負う 輩がいる｡
But there are a few who shine just as bright while they're alive.
These lights are extremely unstable...aggressive, and tinged with sad colors.
その光は
ひどく不安定で 攻撃的で➡
そして 悲しい色を 帯びていた…｡
Knowingly or unknowingly, people are attracted to this light, like moths to a flame.
知ってか知らずか
その光にひかれ 人が集まる｡
そう… まるで 蛾のように…｡
But once I saw that light, I could never live in darkness again.
だが 一度 あの光を見て
もう 闇の中に戻ることは➡
ｵﾚにも できなかった…｡
I, too, am a moth. A moth who fears losing his beacon.
ｵﾚも 立派な 蛾だ｡
再び
かがり火を失うことを恐れる 蛾｡
そして 激しく燃える
かがり火に飲まれまいと➡
A moth, who struggles desperately to avoid being swallowed up by that fiery beacon of light.
必死に あらがう 蛾｡
Moths guided by that beacon's flame. There are moths everywhere...
かがり火を 指針に舞う 蛾｡
どこもかしこも 蛾だらけだ…｡
だが
虫けらに混ざって妙なのが１匹…｡
But amongst all the bugs, there is an odd one among us.
This one is not a moth.
ｺｲﾂは 蛾なんかじゃない…｡
It's extremely difficult to see, but it emits a very faint light.
ひどく わかりづらいが
確かに わずかに 光が見える…｡
It gleams like a sword-a cold steel blade drawn from its sheath.
そう… 例えるなら 刀｡
鞘から抜き放たれた 鋼の刃｡
It's glint is sharp... Silver.
鋭く光る… 銀色だ…｡
だが どうしてかな…｡
But why is it...
どうにも ｺｲﾂの色は…➡
I just can't...
stand its color!
気に入らねえ!!》
(似蔵)人が ひと仕事してる間に➡
Here I thought it was just some random punks barging in to interrupt our work...
不粋な輩が
上がり込んでると思ったら➡
Who'd imagine you were one of them?
ｱﾝﾀも一緒に 来てたとはねぇ…！
(銀時)ぐぅ…！
Did you come to rob the place?
火事場泥棒にでも 来たかい？
What can you do in your condition?
そんな体で 何が できる？
Have you grown so crazy that you don't even know what you're doing?
自分の やってること
わかんないくらい➡
おかしくなっちまったか？
そういうｱﾝﾀも ずいぶんと
調子 悪そうじゃないの～｡
You don't look so hot yourself.
You're pale. Got a stomachache or something? Is it diarrhea?
顔色 悪いぜ｡
腹でも下したか？ んっ！
You're the one with diarrhea.
腹 壊してるのは ｱﾝﾀだろ～!!
うっ…！ うぐぐ…!!
てやっ!!
ｸｯﾌﾌﾌ…｡ おいおい どうした？
Hey, what's the matter? You're bleeding.
血が 出てるよ…？
なっ…!?
Hey, what's the matter? You're bleeding.
おいおい どうした？
血が 出てるぜ！
(笑い声)
(高杉)ﾂﾞﾗ あれ見ろ｡
銀時が 来てる｡
Zura, look. Gintoki's shown up.
(高杉)紅桜相手に
やろうってつもりらしいよ｡
Looks like he's about to take on Benizakura.
(高杉)ﾊﾊﾊ！
相変わらず ﾊﾞｶだなぁ｡
He's as foolish as ever.
It's like taking on a battleship with a rolling pin.
(高杉)生身で
戦艦と やり合うようなもんだぜ｡
♪♪～
He no longer moves like a human.
《桂:もはや
人の動きではないな…｡
His body is crying out because it can't keep up with the Benizakura's commands.
紅桜の伝達指令に ついていけず➡
体が 悲鳴をあげている》
(桂)あの男… 死ぬぞ！
That man is going to die.
ｷｻﾏは 知っていたはずだ！
You knew...
紅桜を使えば
どのようなことになるか｡
what would happen if he used the Benizakura.
You were his comrade. Don't you feel anything?
仲間だろう！
なんとも思わんのか！
ありゃあ
ｱｲﾂが 自ら望んで やったことだ｡
He chose to do that on his own.
If he dies because of it, he gets his wish.
あれで 死んだとしても
本望だろう…｡
(鉄子)本望だと？
(鉄矢)そのとおりだ！
Gets his wish?
That's right! That man truly wished to become a sword!
あの男はな まさしく
刀になることを 望んでいた！
高杉という かがり火を
守るための刀に！
A sword that protects Takasugi, his beacon light!
He'd rather fly into the fire than return to darkness.
再び 闇に戻るくらいならば
火に飛び入り➡
He wanted the power to grow.
その勢いを 増長させるのも
いとわん男だ！
(鉄矢)光に 目を焼かれ
もはや それ以外 見えん｡
His eyes have been blinded by light-he can't see anything else.
How sad and foolish...
なんと… 哀れで愚かな男か！
しかし そこに➡
But inside him is a beauty that transcends good and evil...
その 善も悪も超えたところに
美が ある！
Like a single sword stroke, there is beauty!
ひと振りの剣と同じく
そこには 美が ある！
Swords kill. Master smiths forge swords. What then...
(高杉)刀は 斬る｡ 刀匠は 打つ｡
侍は… なんだろうな｡
are samurai?
(高杉)まぁ なんにせよ➡
And an object that exists for a single purpose is strong, flexible and beautiful.
１つの目的のために
存在するものは➡
強く しなやかで
美しいんだそうだ…｡
Just like this.
ｺｲﾂのように…｡
ｸｸｯ… 単純な連中だろう？
They're simpletons. But I don't hate them.
だが 嫌いじゃねえよ｡
ｵﾚも 目の前の
１本の道しか 見えちゃいねえ｡
I, too, can see only a single path before my eyes.
I don't care if my comrades or anyone falls by the wayside.
あぜ道に 仲間が転がろうが➡
誰が転がろうが かまいやしねえ｡
What's so beautiful about bloodshed?
あれの どこが 美しい？
あんなものが➡
Are you saying that's the goal of your art?
兄者が 作りたかったものだとでも
いうのか!?
もう やめてくれ！
私は 兄者の刀で➡
Enough of this. I don't want to see blood spilt by a sword my brother made.
血が流れるところを
もう 見たくない！
Then why did you bring that man here?!
ならば なぜ あの男を
ここに 連れてきた!?
It's as if you brought him here to be killed!
わざわざ 死にに
来させたようなものではないか！
And with that dull blade of yours.
まさか お前の打った
あの なまくら刀で…｡
You think he can defeat the Benizaka?
(鉄矢)私の 紅桜に
勝てるとでも思う…｡
ううっ…｡
(鉄子/鉄矢)あぁっ…!?
ﾊﾞ… ﾊﾞｶな!?
(物音)
I-Impossible!
He's matched against Benizakura...
《鉄矢:紅桜と 互角…!?
No! He's even stronger?!
いや… それ以上の力で
やり合っているだと!?
そんなはずは…！
It can't be...
Benizakura's been draining Nizo's strength and accumulating data to discover its opponent's weaknesses.
似蔵殿は 紅桜の侵食で
体力が 衰えているとはいえ➡
紅桜そのものは 能力ﾃﾞｰﾀを重ね➡
Benizakura's should be several levels higher.
数段 向上しているはず！
...It can't be.
まさか…！》
(似蔵)うぉぉぉ～っ!!
《あの男…➡
That man...
He's improving faster than the Benizakura?!
紅桜を 上回る早さで
成長している！
いや… あれは➡
No, that's...!
極限の 命のやりとりのなかで…》
In the midst of an extreme fight to the death...
《鉄矢:体の奥に眠る➡
have the memories of past battles lying dormant deep inside his body been awakened?
戦いの記憶が
よみがえったのか!?》
♪♪～
It's the White Knight!
《似蔵:あれが 白夜叉！》
う…｡
It won't go out.
《消えねえ…｡
No matter how many times I try to extinguish it.
何度 消そうとしても…｡
目障りな光が 消えねえ…》
That annoying light won't go out...
(新八)うぉぉぉぉ！
(武市)ふむふむ… 道場剣術は➡
You appear to have studied sword fighting at a dojo before,
ひとしきり こなしたようですが➡
真剣での斬り合いは
初めてのようですね｡
but it seems this is your first fight with a real sword.
You're shaking.
(武市)震えていらっしゃいますよ｡
This is called the Drunken Sword.
[Note: Spoof of that Jackie Chan movie]
これは 酔剣といってな…｡
酔えば酔うほど 強くなる 幻の…｡
A rare form where the drunker I get, the stronger I...
(武市)ﾌｯﾌﾝ… ﾑﾘは
せぬほうがいいですよ｡
Don't force yourself.
ちなみに 私の剣には➡
For your information, my sword style is called Shimura-Ken.
志村剣 といって あの 志村が
ｺﾝﾄのときに よくやる あの…｡
It's what that comedian often uses in his skits.
お前もかいっ！
You, too?!
I'm more of the thinker type, so I usually leave these matters to that wild boar woman.
私はね… どっちかっていうと
頭脳派ﾀｲﾌﾟだから こういうのは➡
あのｲﾉｼｼ女に いつも
任せているんです…｡
(また子)誰が ｲﾉｼｼっすか！
Who're you calling a wild boar?!
Want me to shoot a slug into those lame chicken legs?
その へっぴり腰に １発
ぶち込んでやろうかっ!!
(武市/新八)うわっ｡
(銃声)
A real fight is all about guts, Senpai! It's kill or be killed!
実践は 度胸っす 先輩！
こっちが 殺らなきゃ
殺られるのみっすよ！
♪♪～
《また子:かかった！
Gotcha!
You can't move in mid-air. Die!
空中では 自由も きくまい｡
死ねぇっ!!》
(銃声)
Got her!
《また子:やった…》
♪♪～
You're a hundred years too young to be trying to kill me, little girl!
(神楽)私を殺ろうなんざ
100年 早いね 小娘ぇぇ！
(衝撃音)
(神楽/また子)あっ…｡
Gin-san!
銀さん！
(神楽)銀ちゃん！
Gin-chan.
♪♪～
(また子)なっ なに!?
なんすか こりゃあ！
Wh...What?!
What the hell is this?
…似蔵さん？
Nizo-san?
♪♪～
うわっ！
ぐぉっ!!
ぐふっ…｡
だから… こういうの
苦手なんだってば…｡
I told you, I'm not good at this sort of thing.
先輩！
Senpai!
(また子)似蔵！ ｷｻﾏ
乱心したっすかぁ!!
Nizo! Have you lost your mind?!
(似蔵)ｸﾞﾜｧｧｧｧ…｡
He's conscious... He's being controlled by the Benizakura.
意識が… まさか 紅桜に｡
Tsk, my nasty premonition hit the bullseye!
ﾁｯ 嫌な予感が 的中したっす！
(また子)止まれ 似蔵！
(銃声)
Stop, Nizo!
(また子)ぐっ｡
♪♪～
(似蔵のうなり声)
He's been completely overwhelmed by the Benizakura!
(鉄矢)完全に 紅桜に
侵食されたようだな！
Nizo has lost all sense of self. His entire body has transformed into a sword!
(鉄矢)自我さえない 似蔵殿の
体は 全身 これ 剣と化した！
(鉄矢)もはや 白夜叉といえど
あれは 止められまい！
Not even the White Knight can stop him now!
(鉄矢)あれこそ 紅桜の完全
なる姿 あれこそ 究極の剣！
That is the Benizakura's final form. The ultimate sword!
ひとつの理念のもと 余分な
ものを捨て去った者だけが➡
Such power comes only to those
who discarded all meaningless distractions from their lives and devote themselves to a single goal.
手にできる 力！
There's no way a person like you, always distracted by life's trivial things, can ever stop him!
(鉄矢)つまらぬことに
とらわれる お前たちに➡
止められるわけがない！
Gin-san!
銀さん！
銀ちゃん！
Gin-chan!
《うぁぁ… 消えない｡
Won't... That annoying light...
目障りな光が… 消えない…》
won't go out...
♪♪～
Tetsuko!
鉄子！
死なせない！
I won't let him die! I won't let you kill him!
ｺｲﾂは 死なせない！
I won't let that sword destroy any more lives!
(鉄子)これ以上 その
剣で 人は死なせない！
うがぁぁっ！
(神楽)ﾜﾁｬｰ！
You!
でかぶつ！ その ﾓｼﾞｬﾓｼﾞｬを!!
Let that mop head go!
(鉄矢)あぁっ！
What the?!
Let him go!
離せぇぇ！
うがぁぁぁぁ！
♪♪～
《なぜだ… なぜだ…｡
Why... Why?
Why can't you understand?
鉄子 なぜ 理解しようとしない｡
私は これまで 紅桜に
すべてを 捧げてきた｡
I've given everything I have to create the Benizakura.
Discarded every shred of conscience and restraint.
他の一切 良心や節度さえ 捨てて｡
It's everything to me. If I lose it, then I'll have nothing left.
それは 私のすべてなのだ｡
それを失えば 私には何も残らん》
We suffered a real loss.
((町人:惜しい人を亡くしたな｡
No one else will ever be able to create swords like he did.
(町人)あれほどの刀を打てる
ﾔﾂは もう 現れんだろうて…｡
(町人)息子が いるって聞いたが➡
I heard he has a son. How good is he?
ありゃあ どうなんでい？
(町人)ありゃ ﾀﾞﾒだ｡
He's no good.
Had his father not been Jintetsu, the once-in-a-generation master swordsmith,
(町人)親父が あの稀代の
刀工 仁鉄じゃなけりゃ➡
比べられることも
なかったんだろうが｡
he'd have no problem making a living with his craft.
(町人)まぁ 普通に食ってくにゃ➡
困らねえんじゃねえの))
《鉄矢:あの日から…》
From that day on...
((仁鉄:鉄子… お前は
鍛冶の腕は ﾒﾁｬｸﾁｬだが➡
Tetsuko...your swordsmith skills are rough, but you possess something Tetsuya does not.
鉄矢には ねえもんを持ってる｡
野郎も いつかわかって
くれるといいんだが…))
I hope he understands that someday.
In order to surpass my Father, I completely devoted my life to swordsmithing.
《鉄矢:親父を超えるため
剣だけを見て生きてきた｡
I put my craft before everything else.
すべてを投げうち
剣だけを打ってきた｡
いらないんだ！
I don't need anyone...
I don't need anything but the sword.
私は 剣以外 何もいらない！》
♪♪～
《それしか ないんだ｡
It's everything to me. There's nothing else in my life...
私には もう 剣しか…》
(似蔵)うぅぅぅぅっ！
(鉄矢)鉄子！
Tetsuko!
(衝撃音)
♪♪～
あっ…｡
(鉄子)あっ 兄者！
Brother!
♪♪～
あぁぁぁぁ！
(似蔵のうなり声)
♪♪～
てやっ！
ｸｯ…｡
(神楽/新八)銀さん！
Gin-san!
Gin-chan!
兄者！ 兄者しっかり!! 兄者！
Brother! Pull yourself together! Brother!
Brother...
(鉄子)兄者…｡
ﾊﾊｯ… そういうことか…｡
Now it makes sense...
(鉄矢)剣以外の よけいなものは
捨ててきたつもりだった｡
I thought I had forsaken everything in my life but the sword.
人としてよりも 刀工として…➡
I tried to live my life...not as a human being...but as a swordsmith...
剣を作ることだけに
生きるつもりだった…｡
living only to create swords.
だが 最後の最後で…➡
But when it came to the very end,
お前だけは 捨てられなんだか…｡
you were the one thing...I couldn't give up...
こんな生半可な覚悟で➡
With that kind of halfway commitment,
究極の剣など
うてるわけもなかった…｡
there was no way I could forge the ultimate sword.
よけいなもんなんかじゃねえよ!!
Nothing is meaningless!
よけいなもんなんて あるかよ…｡
Everything matters.
すべてを ささげて
剣を作るためだけに生きる!?
Devoting your life solely to making swords? Is that what a craftsman does?
それが職人だぁ!?
たいそうなこと
ぬかしてんじゃないよ！
Those are noble words. But you just don't want to be bothered.
ただ めんどくせえだけじゃねえか
ﾃﾒｴは！
いろんなもん背負って➡
Don't call yourself a craftsman when you don't even have...
頭かかえて
生きる度胸も ねえﾔﾂが➡
職人だなんだ
かっこつけんじゃねえ！
the courage to shoulder the trials of life.
♪♪～
Watch. See how powerful the things you call meaningless can be.
見とけ
ﾃﾒｴの言う よけいなもんが➡
どれだけの力を持ってるか…｡
ﾃﾒｴの妹が 魂込めて
うちこんだ ｺｲﾂの切れ味➡
Take a good look at this blade your sister forged and see how well it cuts.
しかと その目ん玉に焼きつけな!!
う… うぉぉぉ！
銀さん！ 無理だ!!
正面からやりあって紅桜に…！
Gin-san! That's impossible!
You can't take the Benizakura head on.
銀ちゃん！
Gin-chan!
うおぉぉ！
てやあっ！
((仁鉄:刀なんぞ
所詮 人斬り包丁｡
After all, swords are made for killing people.
どれだけ魂込めてうとうが
ｺｲﾂは変わらねえ｡
You can't change that, no matter how much heart and soul you put into it.
だが だからといって ｵﾚたちゃ
槌を止めるわけには いかねえよ｡
But that's no reason for us to stop wielding our hammer. We'd go hungry.
おまんま食いっぱぐれちまう｡
いやいや それだけじゃねえ｡
No, it's not just that. We are creating more than just weapons.
ｵﾚたちの作るもんは武器だ｡
だからこそ うって うって
うちまくらなきゃならねえ｡
That's why we have to keep on hammering at it over and over.
鉄じゃねえよ ﾃﾒｴの魂をだ…｡
We aren't just forging the iron, but our very own souls.
(仁鉄)鉄を叩き上げながら
ﾃﾒｴの魂を叩き上げろ｡
You hammer your soul into shape just as you hammer the iron.
優しく清廉な人になれ
美しく生きろ｡
Become a gentle person with integrity. Live your life beautifully.
お前らが ちったぁﾏｼになりゃ
それに応えて➡
If you become a good person,
those who would use your swords with decency will be drawn to you.
ｺｲﾂを少しはﾏｼに
使ってくれるﾔﾂが➡
集まってくるだろうよ｡
なぁ おい…
ｵﾒｴはどんな剣をうちたい？
What sort of sword do you want to forge?
…守る剣｡
A sword that protects.
Huh? I can't hear you.
(仁鉄)あん？ 声が小せえよ｡
(鉄子)人を… 守る剣))
A sword that protects people.
♪♪～
It's too...bright...
(似蔵)まぶしくて… いけねえや｡
守るための… 剣か｡
A sword that...protects people... That's so like you, Tetsuko.
お前らしいな… 鉄子｡
どうやら私は…➡
It would seem I haven't hammered long enough...
まだ うち方が
足りなかったらしい…｡
Tetsuko... Become a good...
鉄子… いい鍛冶屋に… な｡
swordsmi...
聞こえないよ 兄者…｡
I can't hear you... Brother...
(鉄子)いつもみたいに…➡
You have to tell me the way you always do...in your loud voice...
大きな声で言ってくれないと…➡
聞こえないよ!!
I can't hear you.
(桂)高杉 ｵﾚは お前が嫌いだ｡
昔も今もな｡
Takasugi, I never liked you. Back then, or now.
(桂)だが 仲間だと思っている
昔も今もだ｡
But you were my comrade.
Back then, and now.
いつから たがった？
ｵﾚたちの道は｡
When did it all begin? When did our paths diverge?
(高杉)ﾌｯ… なにを言ってやがる｡
Hmph. What're you talking about?
(高杉)確かに ｵﾚたちは➡
It's true that the two of us started in the same place.
始まりこそ
同じ場所だったかもしれねえ｡
だが あの頃から➡
But even back then,
ｵﾚたちは
同じ場所など見ちゃいねえ｡
we were heading in different directions.
どいつもｺｲﾂも好き勝手｡
Everyone is doing as they please.
てんで ﾊﾞﾗﾊﾞﾗの方角を…
見て生きていたじゃねえか｡
We've all lived our lives...
looking towards different directions.
Nothing in me has changed since then.
ｵﾚは あの頃と
何も変わっちゃいねえ｡
ｵﾚの見ているもんは
あの頃と何も変わっちゃいねえ｡
What I look towards now hasn't changed a bit.
(高杉)ｵﾚは…｡
I...
Elizabeth-san, we've done all we can do! We can't hold out any longer!
(志士)ｴﾘｻﾞﾍﾞｽさん 限界です！
これ以上 持ちこたえられません！
[For real?]
(志士)桂さんは まだ…｡
Katsura-san is still...
What are those battleships?
(志士)なんだ あの戦艦は!?
(志士)味方の援軍か？
Are they our allies coming to help?
No...that flag is...
(志士)いや… あの旗は…｡
Th-That can't be! What're they doing here?!
ﾊﾞ ﾊﾞｶな！
なぜ ﾔﾂらが こんな所に!?
(志士)春雨！ 宇宙海賊 春雨だ!!
It's the Harusame! The Harusame space pirates!
ﾂﾞﾗ… ｵﾚはな… ﾃﾒｴらが➡
Zura, when you took up your sword for the sake of the country and your comrades,
国のためだぁ 仲間のだめだぁ
剣をとったときも➡
そんなもん
どうでもよかったのさ｡
I could've cared less.
(高杉)考えてもみろ
その握った剣…➡
Think about it.
Who was it that taught us how to use that sword you're holding?
ｿｲﾂの使い方を
ｵﾚたちに教えてくれたのは誰だ？
(高杉)ｵﾚたちに
武士の道 生きるすべ➡
Who was it that taught us the path of the samurai, how to survive and other things?
それらを教えてくれたのは誰だ？
ｵﾚたちに
生きる世界を与えてくれたのは➡
Without a doubt, the man who made us the men we are was...
まぎれもねえ 松陽先生だ｡
Shoyo Sensei.
なのに この世界は
ｵﾚたちから あの人を奪った｡
But this new world...
took him away from us.
だったらｵﾚたちは この世界に
ｹﾝｶを売るしかあるめえ｡
If that's the case, then our only choice is to fight this world.
あの人を奪った この世界を
ぶっ潰すしかあるめえよ｡
To squash the world that took away our master.
(高杉)なぁ ﾂﾞﾗ…｡
Tell me, Zura, what do you think about as you live in this world?
お前は この世界で
何を思って生きる？
(高杉)ｵﾚたちから
先生を奪った この世界を➡
How can we live comfortably and relish life in the world that took our master away from us?
どうして享受し
のうのうと生きていける!?
ｵﾚは ｿｲﾂが
腹立たしくてならねえ！
It makes me angry to no end.
高杉…
ｵﾚとて 何度 この世界を➡
Takasugi...
You don't know how many times I've thought about wiping out this world clean slate.
更地に変えてやろうと
思ったかしれぬ｡
だが ｱｲﾂが…
それに耐えているのに｡
But when I see Gintoki bearing it...
(桂)ﾔﾂが…
いちばん この世界を➡
When I see...
him learning to live in a world he should be despising more than anyone, what can I do?
憎んでいるはずのﾔﾂが
耐えているのに…｡
(桂)ｵﾚたちに 何ができる！
ｵﾚには もう この国は壊せん｡
I can no longer destroy this country.
壊すには ここには
大事なものができすぎた｡
I now have...
too many precious things here I care about.
When I look at you, all I see is someone who can't sheathe his sword.
(桂)今のお前は 抜いた刃を
鞘に収める機を失い➡
ただ いたずらに
破壊を楽しむ獣にしか見えん｡
You've become just a wild beast that enjoys destruction.
この国が
気に食わぬなら 壊せばいい｡
If you don't like this country, then destroy it.
だが 江戸に
住まう人々ごと 破壊しかねん➡
But I won't just stand and watch you destroy the people I care for.
ｷｻﾏのやり方は黙って見てられぬ！
(桂)他に 方法があるはずだ｡
There must be another way.
犠牲を出さずとも
この国を変える方法が…｡
Other ways to change this country without costly sacrifices.
(桂)松陽先生も
きっと それを望んで…｡
I'm sure that's what Shoyo Sensei would have wanted.
(天人)ｷﾋﾋ… 桂だ｡
It's Katsura.
(天人)ｲﾋ… ﾎﾝﾄに桂だ｡
It's really Katsura.
引っ込んでろ！
あれは ｵﾚの獲物だ!!
Stay back. He's mine.
Amanto?!
天人…｡
(高杉)ﾂﾞﾗ… 聞いたぜ｡
Zura, I heard about you. That you and Gintoki beat up the Harusame.
お前さん 以前 銀時と一緒に➡
あの春雨相手に
やらかしたらしいじゃねえか｡
I was trying to link up with them to gain their backing.
ｵﾚはねぇ 連中と手を結んで➡
後ろ盾を得られねえか
苦心してたんだが➡
おかげで うまく 事が運びそうだ｡
But thanks to you, I think it'll go well.
(高杉)お前たちの首を手土産にな｡
When I present them with your head.
高杉！
Takasugi!
I told you... I will destroy this rotten world.
言ったはずだ…｡
ｵﾚは ただ壊すだけだ…
この腐った世界を｡
(志士)春雨が なぜ ここに!?
Why are the Harusame here?!
[Who knows?!]
(天人)ぐっ!!
That damn Takasugi joined forces with the Amanto to destroy the Bakufu!
(志士)高杉のﾔﾂ 幕府を潰すために
天人と手を組んだか…｡
(天人)万斎殿…｡
Bansai-dono...
我らは 桂と くだんの侍の首が
もらえると聞いて… 万斎殿？
We were told we could take the heads of Katsura and that other samurai.
Bansai-dono?
(天人)ちょっと聞いてんの？
万斎殿！
Are you listening, Bansai-dono?
(つんぽ)聞いてるでござる｡
I'm listening. This is Edo's top singer, Terakado...
これね 今
江戸でｲﾁｵｼの寺門…｡
そっちじゃなくて こっちの話！
Not that! What I just said!
Who's this guy? Why'd they send him to negotiate?!
なに？ ｺｲﾂ… なんで
こんなﾔﾂを 交渉によこしたわけ？
心配いり申さぬ…｡
No need to worry.
おおかた 桂が連れてきた
ｻﾞｺでござろう…｡
They're probably just small fries that Katsura brought with him.
すぐにｶﾀがつきますよ｡
They'll be taken care of very quickly.
(志士たち)うわぁ～！
おう！ ｼﾞｬﾏだ ｼﾞｬﾏだ!!
Move... You're in the way!
万事屋 銀ちゃんの お通りでい！
Odd Jobs Gin-chan coming through!
ｲﾃﾃﾃ… 元気いいなぁ ｵﾒｴらよ｡
Ow ow.
You guys sure are full of spirit.
(志士)あ… あれは！
(志士)間違いない あのときの侍｡
Ack... What's that?!
No mistake! It's that samurai...
どけ…！ ｵﾚは今➡
Out of my wayI I'm in a bad mood!
虫の居どころが悪いんだ!!
(志士)桂さん！
Katsura-san!
よぅ ﾂﾞﾗ… どうした？ その頭｡
Yo, Zura. What's with the new hair?
失恋でもしたか？
Somebody break your heart or something?
Shut up. It's a new look. What about you? Get hit by a bomb?
黙れ… ｲﾒﾁｪﾝだ！
ｷｻﾏこそ どうした？ そのなりは｡
爆撃でもされたのか？
Shut up. It's a new look.
黙っとけや！ ｲﾒﾁｪﾝだ!!
(桂)どんなｲﾒﾁｪﾝだ!?
(志士)桂さん ご指示を！
You call that a look?
Katsura-san! Your orders.
(桂)退くぞ…｡
(志士)えっ？
Retreat.
What?!
(桂)紅桜はせん滅した…
もう この船に用はない｡
The Benizakura's been destroyed.
(桂)後ろに船が来ている｡ 急げ！
There's another ship behind us. Hurry.
You're not getting away!
(天人)させるか～！
(天人)全員残らず 狩りとれ～!!
Hunt down and kill every last one of them!
♪♪～
We'll secure your escape route.
退路は ｵﾚたちが守る！
いけ!!
Go.
でも！
銀ちゃん!!
But...!
Gin-chan!
わっ 離すね ｴﾘｰ！
Let us down, Lizzie!
(神楽)銀ちゃ～ん！
Gin-chan!
(天人)いけ～っ！
あの２人の首をとれ～!!
Go! Take their heads!
♪♪～
(天人)ひ… ひるむな～！
押せ押せ!! たたみかけろ～！
D-Don't back down!
Push forward! Forward! Don't give them any openings!
あれが 坂田 銀時と 桂 小太郎｡
So they're Gintoki Sakata and Kotaro Katsura...
強い… 一手
しおうてもらいたいものだな｡
They're strong... I'd like to face them someday.
銀時！
あぁ!?
Gintoki!
Huh?
世のことというのは なかなか
思いどおりにはいかぬものだな！
The world doesn't go the way you hope, does it?
国どころか 友一人
変えることも ままならんわ！
It's not easy changing a friend, much less a country!
ﾂﾞﾗ！ お前に友達なんていたのか!?
ｿｲﾂは勘違いだ!!
Zura, you mean you had a friend? Stop fantasizing!
斬り殺されたいか！ ｷｻﾏは…｡
You want me to kill you?!
銀時…｡
あぁ!?
Gintoki!
Huh?
お前は変わってくれるなよ…｡
Don't change, okay.
お前を斬るのは 骨がいりそうだ｡
It would take a lot of mettle to kill you. I wouldn't take the job.
まっぴら 御免こうむる！
Zura, the day you change, I'll be the first one there to take you out.
ﾂﾞﾗ… お前が変わったときは➡
ｵﾚが真っ先に
たたき斬ってやらぁ！
♪♪～
Takasugi! This is how it is!
(桂)高杉… そういうことだ！
ｵﾚたちは 次 会ったときは
仲間もｸｿも関係ねえ！
The next time we meet, it won't be as friends or comrades!
(２人)全力で
ﾃﾒｴを ぶった斬る！
We'll cut you down...with every ounce of our strength!
せいぜい街で
ばったり会わねえよう➡
So you better watch out.
気をつけるこった！
(天人)おぉ！
Don't bump into us on the street!
(桂)ﾊﾊﾊ… さ～らば！
Farewell!
(天人)逃がすな！ 撃て 撃て～!!
(砲撃音)
Don't let them get away!
Fire! Fire!
That's being well-prepared. Are you Lupin or something?
[Note: Refers to the anime character Lupin III.]
用意周到なこってえ！
ﾙﾊﾟﾝか？ お前…｡
(桂)ﾙﾊﾟﾝじゃない… ﾂﾞﾗだ！
あっ 間違えた 桂だ!!
I'm not Lupin, I'm Zura. Oops, I mean Katsura.
だてに 今まで 真選組の追跡を
かわしてきたわけではない｡
There's a reason why I've been able to give the Shinsengumi the slip all this time.
しかし まさか
ﾔﾂも ｺｲﾂを持っていたとはな｡
But I never imagined he was holding on to this, too.
We all started at the same place. And yet...
始まりは みんな 同じだった｡
なのに…｡
We're now worlds apart.
(桂)ずいぶんと遠くへ
離れてしまったものだな｡
Gintoki... Do you remember this?
(桂)銀時…
お前も覚えているか？ ｺｲﾂを｡
あぁ…｡
Yeah...
ﾗｰﾒﾝこぼして捨てた…｡
I tossed it after I spilled ramen on it.
♪♪～
["Even Mummy Hunters Sometimes Turn into Mummys"]
What? You want me to kill the boss of Odd Jobs?!
Hijikata-san!
[Gintoki is suspected of being an Anti-Foreigner Faction member. Working under Hijikata's order, Yamazaki closes in.]
[Sorachi-san, thanks for the other day. Let's go and have a drink of that with that.]
(ルナ)宇宙開発が さかんな時代｡
ｽﾍﾟｰｽｺﾛﾆｰで➡
何不自由なく 暮らしていた
私たち７人と １ぴきは➡
修学旅行に出発した その日に
宇宙のあらしに あい…｡
(重力あらしの音)
見知らぬ わく星に 流れ着いた｡
そして
私たちの ｻｳﾞｧｲｳﾞｧﾙが始まった｡